<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The counterfeit discover'd.</title>
            <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6948A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174307</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47682882</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47682882</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80819)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2652:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The counterfeit discover'd.</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 4: Thomas Crisp.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ College (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723. --  Counterfeit convert.</term>
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723. --  Innocency trumphant over insolency and outrage of a self-condemned apostate.</term>
               <term>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724? --  Quakerism withering and Christianity reviving.</term>
               <term>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent. --  Animadversions on George Whiteheads book falsly stiled, Innocency triumphant.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172837:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE COUNTERFEIT DISCOVER'D.</head>
            <p>A Pamphlet being deliver'd to the Parliament Titled the <hi>Counterfeit Convert,</hi> &amp;c. wherein I am abuſed, therefore for your Information, I entreat you to read over theſe <hi>Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions,</hi> from which he takes occaſion to purſue his former Courſe of Infamiſing me. I am not ignorant that whoever reproves ſuch a proud and envious Perſon, as this COUNTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FEIFT <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. Whitehead,</hi> getteth himſelf a Blot and Hatred. Notwithſtanding the <hi>Counterfeit</hi> in his Epiſtle pretends a conſciencious Concern for Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet I deſire the Reader to obſerve his Note at the end of his Epiſtle, where he renders his Oppoſers, (<hi>i. e. F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi>) ſuch contemptable and infamous Perſons, that their Names in his Title would obſtruct the reading his Treatiſe: Now I deſire the impartial Reader to judge whether this be not a malicious Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Perſons concerned (in the very intent thereof, and his pretence an untruth as well as a Slander) and much more injurious to <hi>F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> than if their Names had been added to the Titles of their Books in his Title-page. Alſo in order to effect his envious Deſigns in rendring me odious, he <hi>G. W.</hi> in his 74th. Page of <hi>Counterfeit,</hi> &amp;c. he ſays, <hi>T. C's Charge againſt the Quakers, &amp;c.</hi> thereby falſly inſinuating that I charge the Quakers in general, which is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe, and that to his own knowledge; for in my Title-page I charge only <hi>G. W. and his Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors:</hi> Alſo in pag. 7. I ſay, <hi>It's not my intent to Charge the Quakers in general, but</hi> G. W. <hi>and his Abettors.</hi> I ſhall not trouble you with reciting all his wicked Ways and Quibbles he have to cover his Pride, Envy and Falſhood, but ſome few of them for proof. In his Book <hi>Innocency Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,</hi> pag. 75. he ſays, <hi>F. B. Have given them All the Ill-names he can,</hi> which in <hi>Admadverſions</hi> pag. 32. I prov'd to be an untruth; but now the <hi>Counterfeit G. W.</hi> in his 74th. pag. pretends, <hi>he meant All the worſt of Names,</hi> but in this he adds Sin to Wickedneſs, for it is alſo an Untruth as well as the other, although he doth quibble to mend it, for <hi>F. B.</hi> have not given them <hi>All the worſt of Names</hi> as <hi>G. W.</hi> hath given him, <hi>viz. DEVIL in Carnat,</hi> and many more ſuch Hell-fetch'd black-mouth'd Terms, which <hi>G. W.</hi> have in print given <hi>F. B.</hi> which be recited in theſe <hi>Adnimad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 9. Alſo <hi>G. W.</hi> having falſly charged <hi>F. B. That if they,</hi> (G. W. &amp;c.) <hi>cannot for Conſcience ſake pay Tithes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he</hi> F. B. <hi>will not</hi> (ſays <hi>G. W.</hi>) <hi>allow us any favour of the Government, &amp;c.</hi> This I have proved to be a falſe and ſcandalous Accuſation, and a wilful Untruth in <hi>Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions,</hi> pag. 17, for <hi>G. W</hi>'s Abettors having been ſo bold as to publiſh in print this cruel, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Sentence following, <hi>viz. Truth allows no Payment of Tithes at all under the New Covenant, but Condemns it, ſo would you alſo, were your Hearts right in Truth; they who pay Tithes thereby deny Chriſt to be come in the Fleſh, which is a Mark of Anti-chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> and this illegal, uncharitable, cruel Sentence of theirs is in oppoſition to a Chriſtian-Quaker <hi>W. R.</hi> who very Chriſtian-like pleads only for Liberty for ſuch <hi>who can freely pay Tithes without conſtraint:</hi> Yet <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> their Pride and Wickedneſs is ſuch, that they will not allow that Liberty, as is evident by their afore-ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cruel Sentence: Nay, the Counterfeit <hi>G. W.</hi> in his 73d page now affirms, <hi>viz. That our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt Tithes ſhould be maintained, is not a Law of our own making, but of Chriſt's.</hi> But he hath not proved where it is recorded, but I believe it's of the ſame ſtamp, as their Law and great Ordinance, for (Female-Prelates in their Church) Women's-Meetings: Now <hi>F. B.</hi> having (as a Chriſtian ought to do) teſtified againſt this afore-cited unchriſtian Sentence of theirs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it reflects on and condemns, <hi>for Deniers of Chriſt and Anti-chriſts,</hi> all the Martyrs and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, from the higheſt on the Throne to the loweſt, ever ſince the Apoſtles to the end of Time, who pay or receive Tithes; whereupon <hi>F. B.</hi> queried them, <hi>Whether they be of the ſame Mind ſtill, if you be,</hi> ſay he, <hi>How can you have the face to ask any Favour of ſuch, who not only pay and receive Tithes, but make Laws that Tithes ſhall be paid,</hi> &amp;c. From theſe Words of <hi>F. B</hi>'s, <hi>G. W.</hi> forges a falſe Charge, and a groſs Untruth againſt him, as is made appear in theſe <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> pages
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172837:2"/>16, 17, ſo plainly, that <hi>G. W.</hi> cannot but be ſenſible thereof; yet he hath the face in his <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, &amp;c.</hi> page 69, to ſay, <hi>He is ſtill confirmed in his Conſequence,</hi> &amp;c. which is a groſs Untruth and baſe Slander, but his Pride is ſuch that he will not acknowledge his Errour although plainly proved, but deny and call for proofs, hoping thereby to tire and weary thoſe that oppoſe and diſcover his Wickedneſs, and others in reading ſuch Diſcoveries. And for you the 32 <hi>Subſcribers</hi> to <hi>G. W</hi>'s Certificate, I wiſh you had minded that in <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> page 16, and elſewhere, which concern you, and not ſuffered your Names to have been printed again with him, for thereby you own and juſtifie the Wicked, which is an Abomination: It had been more for your Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as Chriſtians and good Subjects, to have appeared to the Parliament in teſtimony againſt that unchriſtian Sentence <hi>(or T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtimony)</hi> as <hi>Counterfeit, &amp;c.</hi> in his 72d. page, as I take his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, terms it; and alſo againſt <hi>G. W</hi>'s groſs Untruths and Slanders, that <hi>G. W.</hi> in his printed Sheet deliver'd to the Parliament. God forbid that any, who for Conſcience ſake, cannot pay Tithes, or other Taxes, ſhould be judged therefore by me.</p>
            <p>For want of more material cauſe of Complaint againſt <hi>F. B. Counterfeit,</hi> in his Epiſtle, makes a huge Noiſe and Bulk now as he did in former Pamphlets againſt <hi>F. B</hi>'s feigned Pillory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for which (as I am informed) F. B. <hi>have acknowledged to</hi> G. W. &amp;c. <hi>that he was ſorry he had done it, and that if it were to do again, he would not do it,</hi> or to this effect; in which he have ſhewn more honeſty than <hi>G. W.</hi> have, for all the Abuſes he have formerly done againſt <hi>F B &amp;c.</hi> as proved in <hi>Animad. pag.</hi> 9, 10, 13. and thoſe which <hi>G. W.</hi> have abuſed, their Reptuations is as valuable as them for whom <hi>G. W.</hi> is ſo much concern'd for, and when <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> have been as honeſt in that caſe, as <hi>F. B.</hi> has been, I dare ſay, <hi>F. B.</hi> will not be backward to give what further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction is needfull; But all <hi>G. W</hi>'s cauſe of Complaint thereabouts is anſwered, in <hi>Animad.</hi> pag. 9.13.18. and I queſtion not, but that on ſerious conſideration of what is there ſaid, the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reader will be ſatisfied that <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> are as much faulty in ſcandelizing as <hi>F. B.</hi> (whom I do not juſtify) and that if any difference be, when the Accompt of Injury is juſtly ſtated, <hi>G.W. &amp;c.</hi> will appear the debtors. And truely <hi>G. W.</hi> if thee canſt accuſe him, and haſt not at the ſame time, ſomething in thine own Conſcience condemning thee for the ſame, thee art to be lamented, as being in a wretched ſtate of hard-heartedneſs; ſee <hi>Animad.</hi> pag. 16, 17, 32, 33.</p>
            <p>In pag. 63. <hi>Counterfeit</hi> ſaith to <hi>T. C. thou would incenſe the Government againſt us, about our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and Non-payment of Tithes:</hi> That this is a groſs Untruth and Slander, may be ſeen in <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mad.</hi> page 14. for its he and his Abettors, having power over other's Conſciences, that I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but for their own Liberty in Marriages and Tithes I never Oppoſed, therefore his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me in the 63d. page, <hi>Thou ſheweth thy ſelf offended, at</hi> G. W. <hi>and his Friends having Liberty,</hi> this is alſo a falſe and ſlanderous inſinuation, by theſe words <hi>(his Friends)</hi> to perſuade the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to believe it is the Quakers in general I oppoſe, when as it is only himſelf, and ſome few ſuch wicked Ones who I oppoſe. In Epiſtle-page 91, ſays <hi>Counterfeit, I being wholly defenſive in my Concern therein,</hi> i. e. <hi>Controverſie,</hi> if this be true, than I pray when, or how, did <hi>T. C,</hi> either Aſſault or Invade <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> in their Rights about Marriage or Tithes. Firſt, As to Marriage, I only maintained my own Liberty and Right, when publickly Accuſed and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed by them. 2dly, For Tithes, the firſt pretended occaſion that <hi>G. W.</hi> took to abuſe me in print about Tithe, was from ſome words of mine in <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtimonies,</hi> page 26. I ſay, <hi>If any obſerve not to do juſt as others in Tithe, or other Civil Rights, the Law requires and ought to be obſerved, unleſs God do by his Spirit forbid, or any for Conſcience ſake refuſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. Now I deſire the Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to judge, if in theſe Words I any ways invaded or prejudiced any in their Liberty, yet this is that <hi>G. W.</hi> and his Abettors abuſed me for, and now in his 63d. page ſays to me, <hi>Thou art greatly concern'd, forſooth,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for Liberty of Conſcience for the free payment of Tithes;</hi> but for all his flouting <hi>forſooth,</hi> I bleſs God I have no cauſe to be aſhamed of what I have wrote therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; and then <hi>Counterfeit</hi> goes on ſaying, <hi>And who hinders ſuch,</hi> &amp;c. In anſwer to this Query, I ſay <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> do, in what they can, or durſt, as is a-fore proved, and in <hi>Animadverſions</hi> pages 16 to 20, therefore the pretence that <hi>He is wholly defenſive,</hi> is <hi>Counterfeit</hi> all over; and ſo is that alſo in beginning of his Epiſtle, <hi>That he is of a peaceable and amicable Converſation, though of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Perſwaſions:</hi> But wherein he is Defenſive, its on behalf of Errour and Wickedneſs, that he excuſe and cover, as is manifeſt <hi>Animadverſion,</hi> the Introduction, pages 3, 4, 38, 39. Nay, for farther proof that his pretence is <hi>Counterfeit,</hi> obſerve that <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> having delivered to the Parlaiment a printed Paper, wherein they had abuſed, and falſly Accuſed <hi>F. B.</hi> as is a-fore, and
<pb facs="tcp:172837:2"/>in <hi>Animadv.</hi> page 16th proved. Now againſt this, and other of <hi>G. W</hi>'s wickedneſs I have teſtified (as I think I ought) for its a great Scandal to the Quakers, nay, to Chriſtianity, that ſuch Falſhoods ſhould be impoſed on the Parliament in the Name of the Quakers, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the whole Body of them are chargeable with his Errours, but my charging only <hi>G. W.</hi> and his Abettors, does take the Scandal off from the whole Body of them.</p>
            <p>I farther deſire the impartial Reader to conſider and judge, whether, or no, them contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Queſtions in <hi>Quaker's Refuge, &amp;c.</hi> page 17, viz. <hi>Whether the firſt Pen-man of the Scriptures was</hi> Moſes <hi>or</hi> Hermes? <hi>Whether there are not many Words in Scripture not ſpoken by the Spirit— but by grand Impoſtors—Some by wiſe Men ill applied—And ſome by true Prophets, yet falſe,</hi> &amp;c. with more ſuch Contempt to Scripture, as in <hi>Quakeriſme Withering,</hi> pages 33 to 36; alſo them contemptable Expreſſions of the Perſon of our LORD JESUS, as <hi>Animadv.</hi> pages 4.35, 36. I ſay, whether theſe and other Wickedneſſes that <hi>G. W.</hi> cover and excuſe, as is proved <hi>Animadv.</hi> be not as great a Scandal to Chriſtianity, as <hi>F. B</hi>'s charging them; and therefore ought to be teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied againſt, becauſe it may tend to excuſe the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Cruelty to our LORD JESUS his Perſon, and in their Infidelity in him: Nay, I queſtion, whether or no, if it were ſeriouſly and ſtrictly conſidered, it may not be a hinderance and ſtumbling-block in the way of the <hi>Jews</hi> Converſion to Faith in our LORD JESUS, as the true and only <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> nay, alſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the <hi>Mahometans.</hi> Let it be ſeriouſly conſidered in the fear of God, I beſeech you, it's this Work, and Principles and Workmen that <hi>Counterfeit</hi> is defenſive in, and prides himſelf in ſaying falſly in his Epiſtle, <hi>Its the Living Truth, and innocent People he defends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with many more of his <hi>Counterfeit Pretences,</hi> theſe being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to prove him an Enemy and Scandal to Chriſtianity, for the contemptable underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing the Perſon and Body of our LORD JESUS, do invalid the Teſtimonies in Scripture, to the great worth and value of his Blood and Death on the Croſs, for that was, as he was the Seed of the Woman and as to his Manhood, and not as the Almighty, Everlaſting God.</p>
            <p>In page 77 ſays <hi>G. W. Where's now the contempt of his perſon?</hi> in anſwer, I ſay, thoſe who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt in words, and had in his Name done mighty Works, yet being workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty our Lord ſaid to them; <hi>depart from me I know you not;</hi> ſo altho <hi>G. W.</hi> in words pretends to own our Lord Jeſus, yet his wicked works of excuſing and covering thoſe contempts, do ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him guilty thereof, for the force of the proof of my charge againſt <hi>G. W.</hi> doth not ſo much depend on his own doctrines, as on his excuſing and covering others as appears in <hi>Animad. Introduct. pag.</hi> 3, 4 and 4.23 to 40. and in <hi>pa.</hi> 25. I do admit <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> in words to pretend to own what in works they deny, and in <hi>Introduct. pag.</hi> 4. I ſay <hi>I fear to avoid contradicting</hi> G. F's. <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> G. W. <hi>do ſtrain and pervert words more than otherwiſe he would do.</hi> And the aggravation of his Wickedneſs is that he do excuſe and cover thoſe contempts contrary to his own knowledge and judgment. To evade my charge againſt <hi>G. W.</hi> as terming the doctrines in difference, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended fudamentals,</hi> now <hi>pag.</hi> 57. he grants ſome of them to be <hi>fundamentals;</hi> but did not ſay ſo before, but if he did really believe ſo, Why did not he defend them, and <hi>G. K.</hi> who aſſerted them? but on the contrary <hi>G. W.</hi> blames <hi>G. K.</hi> and excuſe and cover his oppoſers as is in <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mad. Introduct.</hi> and in <hi>pages</hi> 3, 4, 7. 23. 40. and as for <hi>G. W.</hi> endeavouring to reſtrain his word <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> as onely relating to <hi>diviſion</hi> and not to the <hi>doctrines</hi> in difference; this is ſuch a mean ſhift and quibble that it may eaſily be perceived, for the difference was ſo conſiderably real that there is no colour for that word <hi>Pretended.</hi> And for his acknowledging the Reſurrection of the Body of our Lord, I did not charge him to deny it; but as endeavouring to envalid the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to his Bodily or Perſonal Aſcenſion as aſſerted by <hi>G. K.</hi> and oppoſed by them <hi>G. W.</hi> excuſe and cover <hi>Animad. pages</hi> 34, 36, 37. And for all <hi>G. W</hi>'s pretence of ſincerity, yet he do not plainly acknowledge it; but ſay <hi>the ſame Chriſt that was crucified,</hi> but before his words were <hi>the ſame Chriſt that was</hi> THEREIN <hi>Crucified,</hi> but now he leave out of the Sentence the word THEREIN (on which I ground my Objection) altho he afterwards take it in and ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 58. <hi>Thou Quarrels with the Apoſtles Doctrine,</hi> which is falſe, for they do not ſay <hi>the ſame Chriſt</hi> THEREIN <hi>Crucified,</hi> nor undervalue his Perſon, as they do whom <hi>G. W.</hi> abet.</p>
            <p>In <hi>page</hi> 59. <hi>Counterfeit</hi> queries <hi>where did we ever ſay that he who ſo ſuffered was not Chriſt, but a Vale, a Body—that his Body that was nailed to the Croſs was of a periſhing nature.</hi> In anſwer I ſay I did not charge you as ſaying ſo in thoſe very words in the ſame order ſo as expres'd by you, but I deſire the impartial Reader to peruſe your Doctrines <hi>Animad. introduct.</hi> and <hi>pages</hi> 35, 36.
<pb facs="tcp:172837:3"/>and then judge if I have not proved my charge againſt you; but to prevent you of calling for more proof <hi>ſee Quakeriſm Witherin pages</hi> 16. to 26. alſo <hi>pag.</hi> 47. as follows <hi>the ſufferings of the People of God in this Age is greater ſufferings, and more unjuſt than in the daies of Chriſt, or of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; or in any time ſince: Queen</hi> Mary's <hi>daies brought not forth a ſuffering more crue lin many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, what was done to Chriſt, or the Apoſtles, was chiefly done by a Law, and in great part, by the dre execution of a Law.</hi> Theſe words are ſo contemptious of our Lord's ſufferings and over-valueing of your ſelves, that I want words to expreſs my abhorrance of them, and were there no other proof of your contempt to our Lord Jeſus but this one, its enough (and too much) and I could hardly believe ſuch words ſhould be uttered by any Chriſtian; but I find <hi>G. W.</hi> do not deny them, but ſhuffle and quibble, in <hi>page</hi> 34. to hide and cover this wicked contempt, and excuſe for the cruelty of the <hi>Jews</hi> to our Lord, and the Apoſtles that is expreſt, and implied in them words, inſomuch that <hi>G. W.</hi> is forc'd to <hi>counterfeit</hi> a faint diſlike: <hi>Granting the paſſage not ſo well worded and intended,</hi> &amp;c. Conſider Reader I beſeech you how calm and unconcerned <hi>Counterfeit</hi> is, when our dear Lord and his cruel Sufferings, and the Apoſtles alſo are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptiouſly undervalued; alſo obſerve how furiouſly, and with what indignation he do repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> infamous Apoſtates and ſcandelous to Chriſtianity, in his Title and Epiſtle, and in <hi>Animad. pages</hi> 9. 10. What infamious and ſlanderous Names and Terms he <hi>&amp;c.</hi> gives <hi>F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> alſo the laſt words in the concluſion of my <hi>Animad.</hi> how they Envy and Infamize <hi>T. C.</hi> for preferring the Laws of the Nation before their laws in the form of Marriages and Tithes. All theſe conſidered if my charge againſt <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> be not proved, then let me bear all the blame and ſhame they can put me too. For were he conſcienciouſly concern'd <hi>for the Holy Truth,</hi> as he falſly in his Epiſtle pretends, than he would teſtifie againſt and diſown all thoſe Contempts, with the ſame Earneſtneſs and Zeal as he do uſe to cover and excuſe them, and to defame them that diſcover them; prove your ſelves (to the Parliament and Nation) ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians and good Proteſtants, by your defending and maintaining the Faith in our LORD JESUS, as in Scripture, and the ſucceſſion of Chriſtians hath been believed, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; for and teſtifie againſt, and diſown that blaſphemous Letter to <hi>G. F.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 30 and this afore-cited, and them by <hi>F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> objected againſt in <hi>Animad.</hi> pages 35, 36, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And not by framing a Belief in dubious Terms (that you may make to mean as you pleaſe) and think its enough. You may deceive Men, but God will not be mocked; thoſe that confeſs and forſake their Errours, may hope for Mercy; but them that will not conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs, but cover and excuſe them, ſhall not proſper.</p>
            <p>For <hi>G. W</hi>'s now pretence <hi>pag.</hi> 58. 75. of owning ſome Doctrine of <hi>G. K</hi>'s. cited in <hi>Animad. Introduct. pag.</hi> 2. His ſincerity may be queſtioned; firſt in that he hath taken ſuch pains to blame and aſperſe <hi>G. K.</hi> (tho not by name) the maintainer thereof, and excuſed and covered thoſe who oppoſed him, and aſſerted contrary Doctrines, as in <hi>Animad. pag.</hi> 36. Secondly if he own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them as <hi>fundamentals,</hi> why was he ſo induſtrious to confute the Notion of the Revolution on ſuſpicion that it was <hi>G. K</hi>'s. to infamize him, and alſo for the pious Gentiles to be Chriſtians, <hi>Animad. pag</hi> 38. but all his Charity could not afford any thing in defence of thoſe <hi>fundamental Doctrines,</hi> nor againſt thoſe contrary Doctrines of <hi>G. K</hi>'s Enemeis; now he ſays <hi>pag.</hi> 58. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> have I condemned or oppoſed this Doctrine?</hi> &amp;c. (This, and other his impertinent queries are here afore, and in <hi>Animadverſions</hi> anſwered) but he does not plainly own nor diſown; but excuſe and vindicate the oppoſers thereof; but if he be ſincere let him plainly own them as aſſerted by <hi>G. K.</hi> and diſown the contrary Doctrines of <hi>G. K</hi>'s Enemies, and other unchriſtian Doctrines of <hi>G. Fox,</hi> &amp;c. and then I will acknowledg my ſelf to have been miſtaken, and to have wronged him. But however I bleſs God this advantage is obtained, that the Ancient Chriſtian Faith according to the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> has been of late more Preacht in Meetings than I have heard in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years; in which I rejoice, whatever the end of ſome is.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS CRISP.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_pages">
            <list>
               <item>Directions in what <hi>pages</hi> you may find the charges againſt <hi>G. W.</hi> proved, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Contempt of the Perſon of our Lord Jeſus, in <hi>Introduct.</hi> pag. 3, 4, 23, to 40.</item>
               <item>Contempt of Governours <hi>pages</hi> 11. 16, 18, 20.</item>
               <item>Contempt of Scriptures and over-valuing their own Orders, <hi>pages</hi> 21, 22, 23, 40.</item>
               <item>Blaſphemous expreſſions to, and of <hi>G. Fox. pag.</hi> 30.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:172837:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
